What is today's video about?
today's video will be a summary
of the basic principles of communism,
that is,
If this is your
first contact with communism
maybe this video would be
a good way to start.
And my goal here is to show
the common bases of communism.
And why do I say
'common bases'?
Because there are
different lines of thought on communism.
But I'll present
the common bases
of all these lines.
Except for some
weird sects here and there.
Here we will see
the very basic of the basics.
At the end of this video,
I'll show a reading guide,
Sharing all the books for free
except for one,
we'll talk about
that one later,
and suggest
a reading order, alright?
I strongly recommend
that you read,
and don't only use
this video as a reference.
It's really worth it
to read and reread
even if you already
master the topic
for it to sink
into your head.
It's also worth it to search
for additional bibliography
because what
I will show here
is quite basic, okay?
Quite, quite basic.
So, let's go:
basic principles of communism.
Firstly, I want to thank
Groselha Atômica.
@panquetriste who made
this wonderful art that's here in the screen.
I'd want to thank
Thales Caramante and João Carvalho, too,
who helped me
with the script of this video.
And I beg of you,
Marxologist
who has a PhD in Marxism,
Please, understand
that I'm talking in a basic,
simplified way, right?
You don't need
to quote the Grundrisse,
Or the letters
Marx sent whoever,
just don't, OK?
We know you know
a lot about Marx.
And fine,
we talk about that another day, right?
So, let's go:
What's communism?
Anti-clickbait,
the definition in the screen:
The communism is the doctrine of the conditions
of the liberation of the proletariat.
This is a quote from Engels,
From the book called
“The Principles of Communism”.
So, first of all,
don't be scared of the word 'doctrine'.
Doctrine means
a set of principles.
It isn't like indoctrination,
doesn't conflate 'doctrine' with 'dogma'.
Today there is
a lot of talk about indoctrination,
and people think
this is permanently negative, right?
So, communism is the doctrine of the conditions
for the liberation of the proletariat.
In case someone doesn't know,
what's proletariat?
Proletarians are those
who live from the sale of their labor power,
and who work in exchange for a wage.
This is the proletariat.
Moreover,
what is the goal of communism?
Communism aims for a society
without social classes, that is,
a society without exploitation
of human beings by other human beings.
And a society without classes
can only exist through
a society without private ownership
of the means of production.
And, ultimately,
without State.
It is a society free of exploitation
without social classes,
without private property
of means of production
and without state.
That's it.
This is communism.
Has communism
ever happened in history?
No, the Soviet Union
was not a communist country,
Cuba is not
a communist country,
and China is not
a communist country.
Are there classes?
It isn't communism.
Is there State?
So communism is
where we want to reach.
We'll talk about
what the Soviet Union, Cuba, China, etc are
or were.
So, let's go.
Who outlined
this set of principles for the first time?
Who described it?
Who theorized
this set of principles?
And now
we have to talk about him, right?
Karl Marx.
Marx is the most important theoretician
of all the set of communist principles.
Marx is
absolutely unavoidable.
It is impossible to be
a communist without reading Marx.
Impossible.
First of all:
Are Marxism and communism
the same thing?
No, Marxism and communism
are not the same thing,
but they are deeply connected.
The difference between
Marxism and communism
will be a bit clearer
as our presentation goes,
but remember that
they are not exactly synonyms, okay?
And what Marxism consists of?
What is Marxism?
Marxism contains
three constitutive parts:
three.
philosophical one,
an economic one and a political one.
The philosophical part consists of
dialectical and historical materialism,
the economic part,
of the critique of political economy,
and the political part,
of scientific socialism.
These parts are
not isolated from each other, right?
They are not isolated.
They are intertwined
they interact.
In these three parts
reside the common bases
of any communist.
My goal here is not to tell
the life stories of Marx,
Engels and Lenin, right?
I'll tell just a little of Marx's story
to be a bit clearer about
what I'm wanting to say.
So, in 1818,
Marx was born in a town called Trier,
which was formerly in Prussia,
where today is Germany.
In the 1840's,
he started writing for
a Prussian newspaper
and he was banned from Prussia
because he was
very critical of monarchist politics.
Of Prussian monarchist politics.
In 1844,
he goes to France as an exile,
and he meets a guy called
Friedrich Engels.
The guy with the largest mustache
I've ever seen.
Engels was a son
of an industrial bourgeois
and would become
Marx's friend, intellectual partner,
and patron.
And for those who don't know,
patron is someone who funds some project.
So, yes, Engels was
a bourgeois's son,
but Marx wasn't.
Marx studied Philosophy
at the University of Berlin
and there
he took part in a group
called Young Hegelians.
Here there is an illustration
of the Young Hegelians.
As the name says,
while Marx studied philosophy
in University of Berlin,
he was very influenced by
the ruling philosophy in Germany at that time
which was Hegel's philosophy.
And there,
in the 1840s,
Marx and Engels
start to elaborate
a critique of the Young Hegelians.
They start to differ from
the Young Hegelians
and from Hegel himself.
This critique
that Marx and Engels do
of Hegel
and the Young Hegelians
would comprise
the philosophical pillar of Marxism.
And right there
I want to add a thing, right?
Excuse myself.
Maybe, in this video,
maybe I'll start
with the hardest part.
There are some who say
that the philosophical pillar of Marxism
is the hardest one.
But why did I choose to start talking about it first
if it is the hardest?
Because Marx
formulated the other pillars
of the philosophy.
The philosophical pillar
was the first to be formulated.
And this pillar give us
the Marxist method.
So, if you are having
a hard time understanding it,
know that isn't
uncommon at all.
It is something
that is quite usual.
I took too long to understand
this philosophical pillar.
It demanded
a lot of reading.
What I ask is
that you give yourself a chance to try
To at least get familiar
with this vocabulary.
In the end, as I said,
I'll provide you
with some extra reading
to try to improve
this process a little.
So, let's go.
Returning to the beginning
of our explanation.
You know that communism is
the set of principles
for the working class liberation.
In other words,
to be clearer:
The final goal
is the end of classes,
the private ownership
of the means of production
and the State.
And it must already be popping up
in the minds of some people
who are hearing
this for the first time:
But isn't that utopian?
Is this not idealism?
Have you ever heard
that communism is utopian?
What is a utopia?
Are communists idealists?
Well,
little do people that never
got into contact with communism know
but communism appears
as a critique of utopianism
and a critique of idealism.
Marxism's philosophical pillar
is constituted
as a critique of utopianisms and idealisms
And that's what
we're going to talk about now.
We'll talk about
dialectical and historical materialism
and the name already sounds scary, right?
This a philosophical mouthful,
and that's why I said that I might have chosen
to start with the most complicated part,
but I beg you to give it a chance.
Alright then.
Remember Marx
was a Young Hegelian?
Well, even though
he was a harsh critic of Hegel's philosophy,
Marx was
heavily influenced by Hegel.
But influenced in what way?
Mainly regarding
a thing called dialectics.
So, dialectical
and historical materialism,
we'll begin
by talking a bit about dialectics.
So, what is dialectics?
That's something
we'd need ten volumes to answer,
but I'll try and summarize.
First of all,
Hegelian dialectics
was opposed to another
philosophical method called metaphysics,
which was the dominant
philosophical method up to Hegel.
In order for us to understand dialectics
it's worth it to understand
what metaphysics is
because one thing
makes the other clearer.
That's the part of the stream
where I'll cite the most, OK?
I'll avoid reading
too many quotations
but I think these ones are helpful
because this part is
quite difficult.
Right then,
we’ve said that dialectics
opposes metaphysics.
Engels:
"To the metaphysician,
things and their mental reflexes,
ideas, are isolated, are to be considered
one after the other and apart from each other,
are objects of investigation fixed, rigid,
given once for all.
He thinks in absolutely
irreconcilable antitheses
His communication is
'yea, yea; nay, nay'; for whatsoever
is more than these cometh of evil
For him, a thing either
exists or does not exist;
a thing cannot at the same time
be itself and something else.
Positive and negative
absolutely exclude one another".
That's metaphysics then.
In summary:
metaphysics is a method
that works with isolated,
fixed categories.
Dialectics, on the other hand,
another quote from Engels:
"...comprehends things
and their representations,
ideas,
in their essential connection,
concatenation,
motion,
origin
and ending.
Such processes as those mentioned above are,
therefore, so many corroborations
of its own
method of procedure".
That's referring to
passages from the book I'm quoting
"Socialism: Utopian and Scientific"
by Engels.
Dialectics is the philosophy
that works
with constantly moving categories
that relate to each other
by means
of contradictions, or contraries.
So, a famous example
Hegel gives is
the master-slave dialectics.
In summary, the master can exist
only if there is a slave.
Master and slave
aren't fixed, isolated,
unchanging categories.
The category of master
only exists through
the existence of the slave category.
Within the contradictions
between master and slave.
These categories
change throughout history
but I won't get too much into
the master-slave dialectics.
I'm just showing you
how the categories that dialectics works upon
are interconnected
and ever-changing.
That's it then.
So, according to Engels,
and I think that's a good analogy:
Metaphysics cannot see the woods
for it is worried about the trees.
For him and for Marx,
dialectics was
much more adequate
for understanding
not only natural sciences' phenomena,
but also society's.
An example of dialectics
Engels gives in this book I quoted
is Darwin's
theory of evolution.
Darwin's theory of evolution
was a huge blow to metaphysics
because it works
with transformation,
with historical change
in the very long term.
It made it impossible
to work with fixed categories,
categories
are now changing.
They transform,
they emerge and come to pass
as History goes on.
That's the dialectical principle
of Marx's philosophy,
which is influenced by Hegel.
Let's go to the other part then,
it was dialectical and historical materialism
Let's talk materialism.
Materialism.
I want you to do
a mental exercise now.
Look around you,
wherever you are.
Look around.
Look at everything that surrounds you.
Look if there's
a table nearby, a computer,
a cellphone,
a chair,
anything.
I want you to think about this:
who made these things?
Who manufactured them?
If there's a chair where you are,
who manufactured it?
If there's a couch,
who made that couch?
And further,
who transported it there?
If the couch has metal parts,
who mined the metals?
Whose hands extracted them
from the veins of the earth?
Now I want you to reflect
on how little we think about that.
How little we think
about who made
the objects that surround us.
And no, guys,
it wasn't machined,
it wasn't just machines.
We are surrounded by
an immense amount of human labor.
But we don't realize it.
We're disconnected
from the human labor that surrounds us.
Materialism is the understanding
that material production is
the basis for our social structure.
Not only do we have to think about
who made what is around us
but what surrounds us is
the basis upon
which we organize society.
The two things are connected.
That's materialism's
great trump card.
Let's go back to Hegel for a bit.
Marx incorporated
Hegel's dialectics.
But materialism arises
from a critique of Hegel.
A critique of what exactly?
Hegel was an idealist.
Remember I said Marxism
came around as a critique of idealism?
And this critique of idealism
is mainly a critique of Hegel's philosophy.
So, Marx takes Hegelian dialectics
but leaves out idealism.
Let's use a quotation
from Marx himself then:
“My dialectic method is
not only different from the Hegelian,
but is its direct opposite.
To Hegel, the life-process of the human brain,
i.e., the process of thinking,
which, under the name of ‘the Idea,’
(with a capital “I”)
he even transforms
into an independent subject,
is the demiurges
(for those who don't know, demiurges means deity)
and the real world is only the external,
phenomenal form of ‘the Idea.’
With me, on the contrary, the ideal is
nothing else than the material world
reflected by the human mind,
and translated into forms of thought".
That's a quotation from Capital.
Don't worry,
I know it's complicated but I'll explain.
For Hegel, the reality is
a manifestation of human ideas,
a manifestation of
human thought.
And human thought in its turn
is the manifestation of the original Idea
(With a capital “I”)
that comes
from the deity, from God.
Hegel's philosophy
has a theological outlook.
And the Young Hegelians
were also idealists.
They believed that
what prevented society's development
were the ideas
in people's minds.
There needed to be
a revolution in people's thought
and only then
from reason and thought
we would transform reality.
More than that,
as capitalism developed
there appeared philosophers
that saw what was happening,
the rise of poverty,
misery,
and devised fairer,
more egalitarian societies
that would free all of humanity.
Where?
In their minds.
According to Engels,
the more detailed these societies were,
the further they drifted from reality.
These philosophers became known
as Utopian socialists.
For those who don't know,
utopia is a 'non-place'
Idealism means
you create an idea in your head
and try to apply it to reality.
Materialism
is the opposite of that.
Marx puts this idea
upside-down.
It's not reality
that is created by our thoughts.
But rather our ideas are
an abstraction of reality.
First, we get into
contact with reality
and then we formulate ideas,
not the contrary.
And there is
an inseparable connection
inseparable
between material reality,
the objects that are around us,
and how
we organize society.
These two things
are inseparable.
There's no social organization
without a material backing,
a material substrate.
There's no use
in designing a society in our heads
and trying
to apply it to reality
while ignoring reality itself.
That's materialism.
That's the difference, right?
So, what is material reality?
To make it clearer,
it's not only nature,
but also the way we produce
Remember
I told you to look around?
That is all produced in order to
satisfy our material needs.
We have to sit down;
we make a chair.
That's part of
material reality as well.
But not only that,
our production also satisfies
our cultural
and intellectual cravings.
Not only eating,
clothing, housing
but also what we desire
to consume as culture.
This quote is
by Marx and Engels:
"What they [the individuals] are,
therefore, coincides with their production,
both with what they produce
and with how they produce.
The nature of individuals thus
depends on the material conditions
determining their production."
What we are depends
on how we produce our existence.
What we are depends on
how we eat,
where we live,
what we wear,
on how we wear.
It depends on that,
on how we transport ourselves,
how we satisfy our needs.
So, the way
we produce reality,
we call it
infrastructure.
Our infrastructure is the production
of food, of clothing, of houses, etc.
A social structure arises
over this infrastructure.
We call that
superstructure.
It's what is above the infrastructure.
What is there in the superstructure?
Culture, religion, morals, among other things.
That is, our culture,
our religion,
our morals,
are all above.
They are built upon a material basis.
That is to say,
for example,
that our religion has everything to do
with how we produce
our material reality,
how we produce our food,
our houses,
our clothes.
That is all connected
And we can never lose sight of
the material basis of reality.
One thing depends on the other.
Is this
a mechanical process, though?
Does that mean that every time
we produce food in the same way
the same religion will emerge?
No,
it doesn't mean that the same material basis
will give rise to the same superstructure,
but that the superstructure
is dependent on the material basis.
Dependent.
It is not mechanically
determined by it,
but dependent on it.
This is really important;
once this superstructure has risen,
it impacts back
on the material basis.
So, our culture,
our religion, our morals
can impact
on how we produce our reality.
But it doesn't exist
without that reality.
That's a dialectical movement.
Remember we said
dialectics was important?
In its connections,
in its movement,
and not in fixed categories.
Infrastructure and superstructure
aren't fixed, unchanging categories.
They are connected,
they interact with each other and they move.
I know it's complicated,
but give it a chance
and at least
get familiarized with this vocabulary:
materialism, material basis, infrastructure,
superstructure, dialectics, etc.
Remember it was
dialectical and historical materialism?
Where does
the historical part come in?
This method is such that
Marx and Engels perceive History
through the ways people produced
their reality in order to satisfy their needs
and how that affected
the social structure.
So, for Marx and Engels
the first historical fact is
the satisfaction of our needs.
The first time
a human built a tool
in order to satisfy a need.
That's the first historical fact.
From the moment we satisfy
a need on, we create other needs.
This is the historical process
of creating new needs.
The wheel of History
keeps on turning
as we satisfy our needs.
Marx and Engels
look at History
and ask:
how did they produce?
From this production,
what was the social structure?
How does the social structure
of said society
relate to the way
this society produces?
That's historical materialism.
For summarizing,
there's a quotation that's a bit long,
but it ties together
everything I've said.
"The materialist conception of history starts
from the proposition that the production.
of the means to support human life and, next
to production, the exchange of things produced,
is the basis of all social structure;
that in every society
that has appeared in history,
the manner in which wealth is distributed and
society divided into classes or orders
is dependent upon
what is produced, how it is produced,
and how the products
are exchanged.
From this point of view,
the final causes of
all social changes
and political revolutions
are to be sought,
not in men's brains,
not in men's better insights
into eternal truth and justice,
but in changes in the modes
of production and exchange.
They are to be sought, not in the philosophy,
but in the economics of each particular epoch."
This means that revolutions,
including the bourgeois revolutions,
didn't happen in the way
liberals themselves describe them.
The liberals say people started
demanding more freedom
and that propelled
the revolution forward.
No. Revolutions happen
when our way of producing
and reproducing life changes.
Every revolution has
a material basis, a material substrate.
It doesn't appear in someone's mind and is then
applied to reality because that's impossible,
that goes against
the laws of nature.
And that's what we call idealism.
Marxism emerges as an opposition,
as a critique of idealism and utopianism.
OK? Pay attention to
this last Engel's quote here:
"They are to be sought,
not in the philosophy, but in the economics.”
That's what we are going to talk about now:
the Critique of Economy.
So, one thing that I need you
to pay attention to is this:
Why did I first explain through
the philosophical pillar?
The philosophical pillar
gives us the method.
And Marx and Engels analyze everything
from now using this method.
Dialectical and historical materialism
is always the perspective.
This method is applied to reality
to understand reality.
And now we move on to
the economic pillar of Marxism.
Let's do it!
Remember I said that Marx
was exiled to France and he met Engels there?
So, Engels read Marx's texts
and he criticized Marx's texts
He said: “Marx, there is an economic dimension
missing from your analyses”
Then Marx closed himself
inside a library
and read the writings
of English economists,
especially these two on the screen:
Adam Smith and David Ricardo.
And I need to clarify now:
Can you see that I'm using the term
"Political Economy"
Back then,
"Political Economy" term was dominant
because it was clear that
"Economics" and "Politics" were inseparable.
As the bourgeois economy
was becoming dominant,
they discard the "political" part to give
Economics an alleged neutrality.
“No, no. Economics
has nothing to do with Politics.
Economics is Economics.
It is an exact science,
we conduct a study of reality neutrally."
And for Marxists,
until this day the expression used is
"Political Economy", OK?
Marxists don't disassociate
the economy from politics. Ever.
By the way,
I even put here, look.
For those who don't know,
Marx's masterpiece “Capital”,
“Das Kapital”
it says here:
“A Critique of Political Economy”,
“Capital: Critique of Political Economy",
it's the subtitle.
So, the Marxist economy develops out
of a critique of the political economy
of bourgeois economists.
And some would say,
just to make it clear for you,
some would say
there is no Marxist Economics,
that Marxist Economics is
the bourgeois economy's critique,
but you'll see controversy about it .
Just to let you know
that this exists.
What is the critique of
Marx's Political Economy?
It's an analysis of capitalism,
basically.
Marx lived at a time
when capitalism was already dominant.
But what is capitalism, folks?
What is capitalism?
And I'm telling you,
this Critique of
Political Economy's excerpt
will be where
I'll inject you with
mandatory vocabulary to understand
Critique of Political Economy, OK?
Here we are going to make
a kind of glossary because it's needed, right?
To truly understand; to know how to describe
what these terms mean.
I'm going to talk like that,
with just the cam, and we'll recap later.
Anyway, relax.
What is capitalism?
Capitalism is a mode of production, mode of production.
What is a "mode of production"?
It's the result of interactions between
productive forces and relations of production.
What are productive forces
and relations of production?
Productive forces are
how humans act on nature.
Relations of production are
how humans act on each other.
Therefore, we actuate
on nature and each other
The interaction between these actions
results in the mode of production, right?
Point number one:
What are the capitalist productive forces?
Capitalist productive forces are
the employment of industry, machinery,
automation of energy matrices
and especially division of labor.
In Capitalism,
our work is segmented,
it is broken down into
small specialized parts.
Therefore, our capitalist productive force
isn't just a machine,
but it's how we divide up this work.
What are the relations of production?
We talked about productive forces,
now we have relations of production.
Capitalist relations of production
are based on the exploitation of proletarian
labor by the bourgeoisie, OK?
The foundation
of the relations of production is exploitation.
We are going to
explain about exploitation further ahead.
First of all,
that exploitation is based
on a class division.
What is class?
Class, folks,
is a social division of labor.
Are there classless societies?
Yes.
In classless societies
everyone has to work,
everyone benefits
from the fruits of labor,
and the labor is divided
by ability or skill.
This type of division
we call "Natural Division".
In class societies,
there is no natural division,
there is a social division.
And what does it means?
Imagine that
you work in a factory.
The factory owner isn't
less skilled than you to work in the factory.
So, why do you work at the factory
and he doesn't?
Since he has
the same skills as you.
Because he belongs
to another class.
What determines the class is which position
you occupy in the production chain.
And under capitalism,
these classes are increasingly comprised
of the bourgeois, In other words, the class that
doesn't work and owns the means of production,
and proletariat, the class
that does work and owns nothing
other than their work force.
What divides these classes is
not skill, nor ability, not even vocation,
it is a social division.
Well then, another characteristic
of relations of production.
We have classes
and one of them owns
the means of production,
that is, these means of production are
private property of someone.
One of the central characteristics
of capitalism is the private property.
What is private property?
There is a classical definition
From the bourgeois economists themselves:
Private property is
the free disposal of another's labor power
When we are talking about
private property,
we are talking about private property
of the means of production.
Why did private property,
and only "private property",
become synonymous with private property
of the means of production?
Because the private property
of the means of production was
the first form of private property.
So, in the time of
Marx, Smith, and Ricardo,
talking about private property meant
private property of the means of production.
Back to definition:
Private property is the free disposal
of another one's labor power.
An example:
remember that mode of production
is the interaction between
productive force and relations of production?
Did we have other modes of production?
Yes.
We had, for example,
the feudal mode of production.
the slave-owning mode of production.
For example,
in the slave-owning mode of production.
What is private property
in the slave-owning mode of production?
The slave.
Remember that private property is
the free disposal of another one's labor power?
How does the slave owner dispose
of the labor force of others?
By owning the person
Another person's work is
freely available to the slaveholder.
The person is
the owner's private property.
How this works in capitalism?
People are not the property
of the capitalist,
but the capitalist owns
the means of production.
Means of production, that is,
what is necessary for executing labor
is taken from the hand of workers,
and the capitalists controls the worker's
productive forces through wage labor.
Workers are forced to sell
their labor power
to work on the means of production
that have been taken from their hands.
And how this capitalist can take
these means of production
out of the worker's hand?
Because he owns
something called "Capital".
What is capital?
Capital can be summed up
in a simple few sentences
"Capital is value that creates value";
"resources that create resources";
"Wealth that creates wealth"
Capital is money?
No.
But capital can be money?
Yes.
They aren't synonymous,
it's that what I mean.
What you have
in your wallet now isn't capital, OK?
Capital is a resource
that can be in form of money
that is used
in the acquisition of means of production.
Factory, machine, land,
energy, raw material
and workforce.
Once such means are acquired
they become part of the capital.
So, factory, machine, energy,
and raw material are part of the capital, OK?
That's why capital
isn't just money.
Therefore, in short,
capitalist relations
of production are based
on class division. One class
owns the means of production and doesn't work,
and the other only owns
its own labor power and has to sell it.
This brings us to the last characteristic
of relations of production:
the Commodification
of Social Relations.
In capitalism, the commodity
is the center of social relations.
In capitalism,
we don't produce our existence,
we buy our existence.
You don't produce your food,
you buy your food.
You don't sew your clothes,
you buy your clothes.
You don't build your house,
you buy your house.
And you sell
your labor force too,
your labor force
becomes a commodity.
But what is a commodity?
A Commodity is something that is produced
for someone else's consumption,
and to be traded on the market.
This commodity element
deserves more attention.
Because, again,
as a commodity is the center
of all social relations in capitalism,
it needs to be understood.
Before that,
let's review everything.
Vocabulary:
Mode of Production: interaction between
productive forces and relations of production.
Capitalism is a Mode of Production.
What are Productive Forces:
how humans act on nature.
What are Relations of Production:
how humans act on each other.
What is Class:
social division of labor
(as opposed to the natural work division),
position occupied
in the productive process.
Is class determined
by how much money you make? No.
If you earn wages,
you are a worker, OK?
you are a proletariat.
"Oh, my salary is 100k/month",
Class is determined
by the social division of labor.
by where you are in the productive process.
What makes it so confusing is
that, nowadays, we use such terminology
as "upper class", "middle class",  "lower class".
What determines class for Marxism is
the position you occupy
in the productive process,
Right? So that's right.
Private Property:
free disposal of another's labor power.
Remembering that we are talking about
the private property of means of production.
It's not your house,
your old truck, or your flip-flops.
Means of production:
what is necessary for the execution of work.
Factories, raw material, energy.
Capital:
value that creates value,
resource that creates resource,
wealth that creates wealth.
Commodity: something produced
to be consumed by others,
and to be sold in the market, okay?
OK? Let's keep going!
Let’s move on to a subject
that is a bit more complicated,
but fundamental to our understanding
of Marx's critique of Political Economy.
Remember that the commodity
is the center of our social relations?
This commodity has
something called Value.
So, the question
that comes up is:
what is Value?
How is Value determined?
OK, so I'll begin with a quote
hat made me understand Value
once and for all.
But I'll start with the quote
and then we are gonna describe Value,
not the contrary.
"...if I say a quarter of wheat
(quarter is a unit of measure)
exchanges with iron
in a certain proportion,
or the Value of a quarter of wheat is
expressed in  a  certain  amount  of  iron,
I say that the Value of wheat
and its equivalent in iron
are equal
to some third thing,
which is neither
wheat nor iron,
because I suppose them to express
the same magnitude in two different shapes.
Either of them,
the wheat or the iron,
must, therefore,
independently of the other, be reducible
to this third thing
which is their common measure."
I've never forgotten this quote.
If a certain amount of wheat
is equal to a certain amount of iron,
it does not mean that one is the same as the other,
but that they are equal to a third thing.
And this third thing is Value.
OK, so,
Value.
Value is maybe one of the most complicated
concepts of Political Economy,
even Marx recognized that.
Marx says
in the Introduction to Capital
that the first chapter was the most complicated,
and it is the one in which he describes Value
We have
commodities in society,
we buy our things.
These commodities have Value.
Do you remember
when I told you to look around?
and think about
who made the things you have?
All the objects you possess,
all of them,
without exception,
have one substance in common.
Do you know what this substance common
to all the things you have is? Labor
Labor, folks, is
a social substance.
Every commodity has in it
some amount of crystallized labor.
Is Value the same thing as price?
No, no.
Is price Value, chat?
No.
Every time you think you're not
understanding what Value is,
be sure you're not
confusing it with price, OK?
So,
what determines the Value of
a commodity?
The labor is socially necessary
for the production of this commodity.
Folks, what has more Value,
a glass or a car? A car.
Why?
Why? Because the amount of labor
needed to make a car is way bigger.
Making a car requires way more labor
than making a glass.
Therefore, a car has
much more Value than glass.
Does this mean that if I had a glass factory,
and it took me the same amount of time
needed to make a car, to make this glass,
the glass would get more expensive?
No, OK?
No.
For the love of God, no.
Value is determined by the amount of
socially necessary labor.
The social criteria are fundamental.
What determines Value is the amount of labor
in a certain social state
and under
specific productive conditions
of an entire society.
It's how much labor is required
to produce a glass in the entire society,
and not how much you, an individual,
needs to produce a glass, OK?
So, if Value is not price,
what is price, then?
Price is
the expression of value as money
an expression in money.
Price usually
gravitates around value.
This price
gravitates around Value,
Adam Smith,
not Marx,
called it central price.
Once a commodity is produced by labor
and it goes out
to be sold on the market.
It (the commodity) will get
closer to its value.
Value is not price,
value is a property of the commodity,
and value is determined by
the amount of socially necessary labor.
Remember we said that the commodity is
the center of all social relations?
In Capitalism,
our labor power is also a commodity.
We sell our labor power
at market price.
If our labor power is
a commodity,
and value is a property
of a commodity,
What is the value of
our labor power?
The value of our labor power is also
determined by the socially necessary labor,
but in another way,
the value of
your labor power is
determined by
all that reproduces you.
It's the value of
everything you need to exist.
Food, clothing,
roof, heating, etc.
All that
you consume to exist
has in it the socially necessary labor
needed to produce it.
The Value of your labor power
is the sum of the values of
all the things you need to exist.
And, in Capitalism,
especially, with an extremely
unqualified workforce,
the labor power's value gets close to
the bare minimum you need to maintain yourself
So, when you sell your labor power
on the labor market,
that's why we call it
the labor market,
you are selling it
by its value,
and the value of
your labor power is determined by
what you need
to keep existing.
And this you can derive
from reality, folks.
Your salary is being paid to you so that
you can buy what you need to continue existing.
Why is all of that so important?
Because understanding
what value is makes us comprehend
the greatest discovery of
Marxist Political Economy,
which is Surplus Value.
Without understanding value,
we would not understand the surplus value.
Without understanding surplus,
we would not understand capitalism.
"Surplus" can also be "surplus value".
Got it? To understand surplus value,
we need to understand value.
So:
according to Engels,
the discovery of the surplus value is
a discovery of the same magnitude
as Darwin's Theory of Evolution
Why?
Because it can expose, strip naked,
the internal mechanisms of exploitation.
When we talk about
exploitation in Capitalism, folks,
we are not judging it.
We are describing
the mechanism of Capitalism.
Talking about exploitation in Capitalism
isn't a judgment on moral grounds,
it's merely descriptive.
And this is only understood when
you understand what value and surplus value are.
So, let's go over it again:
what determines
the value of a commodity
is the socially necessary labor contained
in this commodity.
Who does this labor?
It's the worker,
not the bourgeois.
The bourgeois doesn't work,
who works is the worker.
Very well, after working and creating this value,
in exchange, the worker earns a wage.
But the wage of the worker is equal
to the value of his labor power,
and not the value
they created while laboring!
That means that while the worker is working,
and laboring, they create value, create value,
but they earn the equivalent of the value of
the labor power in the form of a wage.
That is, what they create has
no connection with what they earn.
What they earn has a connection
with what they need to live.
Imagine the following:
If you have an 8-hour workday
and in four hours you produce
the value equivalent to your salary,
the other four hours
you worked for free.
This free labor
we call surplus labor.
The value created
in this surplus period is
appropriated by the bourgeois
in the form of surplus value.
Surplus value is the mechanism
by which the bourgeois profit.
And we have three types of surplus value:
absolute, relative, and extraordinary.
Absolute surplus value expands
as the labor hours expand.
Remember what I said?
You need 4 daily hours to generate the value of
your salary, and your workday has 8 hours.
Out of a sudden, your workday goes up to 10 hours,
without a wage increase.
You've created
more surplus value.
Absolute surplus value: the workday increases,
so the capitalist's profit increases.
Now, relative surplus value is:
imagine that you work 8 hours a day,
but the factory got optimized.
Instead of producing x chairs,
you produce, in the same amount of time, 2x chairs.
But you earn the same salary.
You relatively increase the extraction of value;
the labor time needed is the same,
but you can produce way more.
And the extraordinary surplus value has to do
with the production of the same objects,
of the same commodities,
but in other companies.
For example:
if there are many companies
producing chairs,
and one of them discovers
a much faster way to produce,
when this commodity
goes to the market,
it, being sold at a similar price as the others,
will yield more profit.
So, extraordinary surplus value
is relative to the industry as a whole,
when some company discovers
a way to lower their costs.
This surplus value tends
to find an equilibrium in two ways:
either when some other companies
also gets optimized,
or when all the others go bankrupt,
creating a monopoly.
The point is: the final goal of every bourgeois is
the increase in surplus value.
The increase.
This is not moral judgment.
Marx at no moment makes
some moral judgment.
He doesn't say "it's bad", "good",
"ugly", "stupid", or "blockhead".
Saying that the goal of the bourgeois is
the increase of surplus value is descriptive,
because this is observable,
we can verify it in reality.
And what is important here?
As profit is extracted
utilizing the surplus value,
the bourgeois incorporates
this profit back into their capital.
When the surplus value is extracted,
the bourgeois reinvests it in production
to increase the extraction of surplus value.
They refine more
this extraction each time more
in an endless
and unceasing cycle.
Capitalism has shown
a cyclical crises since its beginnings.
Already in the 1870's,
Engels talked about seven crises of capitalism.
Seven!
In the 19th century.
This is when capitalism was
way smaller than it is today;
when it was restricted to
just a few of countries.
So, let's wrap it up?
Marx's critique of Political Economy
focuses on analyzing capitalism.
Capitalism is a mode of production based
on the employment of big industries.
in the division of labor,
in class society, in private property,
in the commodity as center of social relations
and constant expansion of capital.
Let's recap some concepts.
We have seen the value
and surplus value.
Value:
it is a "property of the commodity.”
And this property
is "determined by the socially necessary labor.”
Surplus value is the "value created by the worker
which is appropriated by the bourgeois",
and that doesn't return to the worker.
This surplus value can be:
"absolute",
when the working hours increase;
"relative",
when productivity increases;
"extraordinary" when the productivity
in comparison to other factories increases.
OK?
And why is it all that important
Weren't we going to
talk about communism?
Why are we talking
so much about capitalism?
Understanding the capitalist
mode of production is necessary
so we can walk towards
some other mode of production,
and transform our productive forces
and our relations of production.
Remember we said that Marxism and Communism
have an aversion towards utopianism?
Towards utopia, idealism?
Every Marxist analysis,
starts from material reality.
This is Marx's object of study:
observing capitalism's reality,
the reality in which he was living.
OK?
And then,
we go to the last pillar of Marxism,
which we call
scientific socialism.
So, by now we've got a basic,
and I mean really basic, analysis
of the way capitalism works,
then what?
We've seen that capitalism exploits us
and throws us into poverty.
So, what to do?
Very well,
capitalism has developed
our productive forces in a way never seen before.
It brought an unprecedented level
of productivity, unknown to humanity by then.
However, at the same time, it threw
a huge part of humanity into misery,
excluded from society
A huge chunk of people was proletarianized,
lost everything they had,
and turned to sell their work force
in exchange for the bare minimum to survive
while bearing
strenuous work hours.
So,
how did we sharply increase
productivity and poverty at the same time?
How did we increase
machinery and automation levels
and work load simultaneously?
Why is it that there's more and more automation
and work load never decreases?
Those are the contradictions
that will be our aim in this next analysis.
Okay, next:
"Analyzing Capitalism",
We've concluded
that capitalism is based on exploitation, right?
Very well,
The first thing
we can know for a fact is:
there's no exploiters without the exploited,
this has always been the case, right?
Were there always
exploiters and the exploited?
Let's dig into that.
We know also
that the mechanism of exploitation comes
through private property.
Marx, through the method
(dialectical and historical materialism),
come to the reasoning that
there has not always been private property.
And not just that,
he also found that there's been different kinds
of private property throughout history.
The same goes to social classes,
those weren't always in the scene,
throughout history,
social classes are quite a lot different.
It's that the existence of social classes
and private property
Is linked to a certain phase of
the development of production.
What's so relevant about that?
This conclusion by Marx
makes us be able to see that
These social organizations,
these human organizations,
are not indispensable.
Private property isn't indispensable
for human society.
Social classes aren't imperative
So, the notion that there will always be
employers and employees is false.
Not only this,
through the material analysis of capitalism,
Marx got to the conclusion
that we already have resources
to march towards another society,
With different social relations.
So, let's go,
a little quote from Marx here
for us to discuss,
from the Communist Manifesto:
"an epidemic that, in all earlier epochs,
would have seemed an absurdity
— the epidemic of over-production.
The conditions of bourgeois society are too
narrow to comprise the wealth created by them"
What does Marx mean here?
By the first time in history,
human society was dealing
with the inverse of its usual problem.
Until then, society had only dealt
with the issue of lacking production.
Society had a scarcity issue.
The capitalist mode of production
brought a new problem:
excess of production.
The catch is:
there's only excess
of production in capitalism,
for the capitalist means of production
are illogic, irrational.
Capitalism does not produce
to satisfy our needs,
it does to sate
the needs of the capital.
If production doesn't become capital
it is disposed of.
Meaning,
the capitalist means of production
jeopardize our production capability.
We're hindered from producing
more and better due to capitalism.
So according to Marx,
the capitalist ways are obsolete.
OBSOLETE.
They need to be transformed.
Is such transformation possible?
Not only possible.
according to Marx,
it's very likely.
Why?
Throughout capitalism's development,
it creates its own contradictions
which will bring its downfall,
unavoidably
By expanding,
capitalism generate proletarians,
proletarian by proletarian,
more, more and more
This class that it creates is
the one that antagonizes it.
Marxism's greatest asset was to perceive
that there are not only classes,
and that those classes are
unavoidably antagonistic to each other.
They'll never reach harmony,
for they have contradictory interests.
To this antagonism between
the two main classes of capitalist society,
we call class struggle.
Class struggle.
For Marxism,
every doctrine,
each and every set of principles
that attempts to balance classes,
and harmonize classes
are utopian.
It's fallacious.
It's a facade.
If there is an exploited class,
there will be an exploiter class above it
Every time.
The Utopians,
which we talked about before,
had no perspective
of any class.
They sought a society
that balanced all of humanity.
having the perspective of the classes is
knowing that they are antagonistic.
it is fundamental
to what we call Scientific Socialism;
which is how Engels name it.
This expression appeared
to contrast with Utopian Socialism.
So, why does this matter?
According to Marx,
the class struggle
between the bourgeoisie and the proletariat
will lead
to a rupture with capitalism.
What's relevant about Marx is
that not only does he identify the classes,
But he also credits the revolutionary protagonist
to the exploited class.
The proletariat becomes
the revolution's Subject.
The proletariat belongs
to the class that will conduct revolution,
unlike the Utopians.
Utopians believed
that the working-class were
unable to lead any change.
That any change
would come top-down.
Marx said otherwise:
it will come bottom-up.
And how will this rupture
be conducted?
The proletarian class,
becoming aware of itself,
will organize
And seize the power of State
and institute something called
the dictatorship of the proletariat.
What does dictatorship
of the proletariat mean?
To Marx, we live in a dictatorship
of the bourgeoisie.
The State does not arise as
an apparatus that balances society.
You'll see idealists,
to this day,
saying that the State arises
to reduce society's conflicts.
No.
For Marx, the State is
an apparatus of specific class violence.
The State arises so the ruling class maintain
the ruled one in its due place,
through violence.
In the capitalist society,
who has the State apparatus
is the bourgeoisie.
The State is puppeteered
by the bourgeoisie
to maintain the bourgeoisie on power.
Alright?
So, for Marx, we live in something called
the dictatorship of the bourgeoisie.
If there is capitalism,
there's dictatorship of the bourgeoisie.
Well, if the State is necessarily
an apparatus of
specific class violence,
when the working-class
takes the State,
won't it still be that?
Yes, exactly.
But this pyramid
will be turned.
The State is an apparatus of
specific class violence;
with the working-class taking
the State apparatus,
it will use the State apparatus for,
through violence,
eradicate the bourgeoisie as class.
The State is an apparatus
of specific class violence,
and it will still keep being as such.
So, the State
in the hands of the working class
will oppress the bourgeoisie
until it vanishes,
and while
the other classes vanishes,
the State becomes obsolete.
Once there are no more classes
to oppress,
the State no longer needs to exist,
and it languishes.
It disappears.
It becomes useless.
That's Marx's vision of the transition
from socialism to communism.
That's the way the State dies out
in the Marxist point of view.
Alright?
So, let's recapitulate.
"The scientific socialism: demonstrates
that the existence of classes
it's connected only to certain phases
of production development.”
Once, they did not exist.
They can cease to exist.
With the private property,
it's the same thing.
"The class struggle conduces,
necessarily, to proletariat's dictatorship",
and "this dictatorship is nothing more
than the transition to abolition of
all classes, and to a classless society."
That's Marx's great discovery.
And here, we have to make
a small observation:
I've been using the terms
socialism and communism,
but we need to distinguish
one from the other.
So, firstly:
socialism and communism
only have the meaning they have today
after the Russian Revolution.
So,
Socialism is
the step of the transition to communism.
During socialism,
the working class will be at power
and it will oppress the bourgeoisie
until the classes vanish.
During communism,
the classes no longer exist.
Marx doesn't use these terms.
Marx uses
"the first stage of communist society"
and "superior stage
of communist society".
The reason behind it, after
the Russian Revolution, the terms are switched,
it's historical,
and it has the reason to be so.
It made sense
at the time it came about.
But do know that, from now on,
I will use "socialism" as transition
and "communism" as destination.
Another thing: Marx doesn't determine
the specific characteristics of socialism.
Marx was a materialist.
For him, any prediction
or recipe was idealism.
All societies should start
from a material analysis. A real one, OK? Not ideal.
Marx can't make the same mistake
he criticized in the Utopians.
So, Marx only presents
general ideas:
socialism is the working-class at power,
dictatorship of the proletariat
and transition in direction of
a society without classes.
That's why every time someone asks
"how many brands of washing powder
will exist in socialism?",
anything we could answer
is going to be speculation.
There's no way to know.
We'll know the details
from experience.
And the soviets detail
much more about what is socialism. Why?
Because they had a socialist experience!
Marx didn't.
Therefore, he didn't dare to predict the future
beyond what he knew was possible.
He knew it was possible
that the working-class take the State apparatus;
That it was possible for the workers to use
the State apparatus to oppress the bourgeoisie;
He knew it was possible.
And it was possible.
And it was done!
All of this came from
the material analysis.
Another thing:
that means that, after the revolution,
on day one of socialism,
all the contradictions will go away?
Contradiction's gone.
The capitalism died,
any opposer died, and everything died. No.
Marx's quote:
"What we have to deal with here i
s a communist society,
not as it has developed
on its own foundations,
but, on the contrary,
just as it emerges from capitalist society;
[a communist society],
which is thus
in every respect,
economically, morally, and intellectually,
still stamped with the birthmarks of
the old society from whose womb it emerges".
So, just remembering:
in this quote,
Marx is using the word communism
as we use the word socialism today, alright?
Here, Marx is talking about
the first stage of communism.
That's why I had
to clarify the vocabulary here.
What's the point here?
A society that comes
from the womb of another,
and with that it carries
its birthmarks.
If we have a capitalist, sexist society
and we go through a revolution,
the new society
will still be sexist.
This contradiction
will not disappear.
The question is, the new society gives us
the possibility to overcome sexism,
while capitalism doesn't.
Capitalism doesn't give us the opportunity
of overcoming many contradictions.
So,
Oh, but what about Cuba?
wasn't Cuba misogynist? wasn't Cuba homophobic?"
Cuba came from
a misogynist and homophobic society.
It would be strange if it wasn't so anymore
on day one of the revolution.
So, we can't
generalize socialism as well,
because each socialist experience will emerge
from a different capitalist experience;
with their own particularities and with
their particular contradictions. Alright?
That was all about Marxism.
We have:
dialectical and historical materialism,
political economy, and scientific socialism.
Now, we go to the last basic part
which is necessary and essential.
We're going to talk
about Lenin now.
This Lenin, here. So, let's go.
Why are we talking about Lenin?
By now, you should know
that the first successful revolution
of a socialist nature was
the Russian Revolution of 1917.
On the Russian Revolution,
and the whole Soviet experience,
I would need to do
a separate video.
Today we are going to talk about
the greatest leader of this revolution,
which is Vladimir Ilyich Ulianov,
or Lenin.
Because Lenin is the greatest Marxist
after Marx and Engels.
For those who don't know,
Lenin is a great theoretician.
And not only big,
but he is also unavoidable.
It was because
of Lenin's theoretical work
that the Russian Revolution was possible.
And why is Lenin so important?
Because Lenin gives
an operational dimension to Marxism,
he develops a method
for the practical application of Marxism.
And there are several elements
of what we call Leninism today,
but today I'm just going to talk about one,
which is perhaps the main one,
which is the party.
And come on,
let's talk about the party.
Since the time of Marx and Engels,
it was already known
that it was necessary to organize the class.
What did Lenin do?
He observed reality,
just like Marx and Engels did,
he saw how the class
was organized,
and proposed
a new form of organization.
This new form of organization
is called the Leninist party.
And then arises the question:
when we think of a party,
we think of abbreviations
that run for the parlament.
run for Congress, run for the Executive.
I'll tell you something
in advance:
that's not
what a Leninist party is about.
In fact, it has no intention
of winning the election, okay?
The Leninist party does
not come about to win elections.
What is the Leninist Party?
The Leninist party is
the organized detachment of the working-class.
Lenin used to say,
his quote:
“In its struggle for power the proletariat has
no other weapon but organization.”
The Leninist party,
unlike parties running for elections,
organizes itself
on a revolutionary basis.
The party's idea is to prepare
and mobilize the class to take power;
not in a peaceful way,
but in a combative way.
The seizure of power needs
to be done in a combative way,
because the ruling class
will not voluntarily relinquish power.
In Russia, that party
was the Bolshevik party.
What are the elements of this party?
Firstly, the party must be
the vanguard detachment of the class.
What does vanguard mean?
Vanguard is a military term.
Vanguard means who is in front,
it is the opposite of rearguard.
The vanguard is
the best elements of the working-class:
the most experienced,
most dedicated, most revolutionary,
most enlightened workers.
That party must arm itself
with a revolutionary theory;
Another quote from Lenin,
also famous:
“Without revolutionary theory
there can be no revolutionary movement.”
But this party
cannot serve only to absorb
what the working class thinks.
The party appears, and then the idea
is not to see what the working class is thinking
and represent the class
from what it is spontaneously thinking.
The party has to arm the class
with revolutionary theory;
because, for Lenin, the working class
organizes spontaneously.
But this working-class organization
is limited.
The class,
when organized spontaneously,
usually fights for the improvement
of their immediate condition
— salary improvement,
reduced working hours, labor rights —
but it does not fight towards
overthrowing the system.
Why it is so?
Because it cannot see
the mechanism of this system.
Since capitalism is a system,
it is a synthesis, it is an abstraction,
you cannot approach the worker,
point and say “capitalism is there”.
But they can see
that they can't pay the bills,
they can see
that they are working too hard,
and they can see that
when they get sick they get screwed.
They can see all of this.
And then the class
will organize itself.
But the party cannot
just absorb this demand.
It has to arm the class
with something else.
And that something else
is the overthrow of the system!
That's why this party needs
to be leading the class.
And mind you,
it's not above!
It's not above.
It's ahead! It's ahead.
The party has to be
the political leader of the class. Why?
Because it can arm the class
with revolutionary tactical theory.
But this party can never
disconnect from the masses.
It has to have the advanced
detachments of the class,
but not isolate himself from the class.
It has to be connected
to the masses
and has to convince
the masses.
The party needs to work closely
with the entire working class
to gain moral credit
and political credit
through example,
through persuasion.
And for that, it needs to be organized.
What does that mean?
Within a Leninist party,
discipline must be ironclad
but willing.
When you join the party,
you willingly submit
to iron discipline.
And this is to awaken
the revolutionary spirit in the classes,
through example.
Does this mean that the party
should be the only organization?
It does not.
Should not. Cannot even.
Society must have
a series of class organizations:
Unions, cooperatives,
organizations, associations, and youths.
In the case of Russia,
there was a very important one: the soviets.
The soviets, folks, were the factory councils
that were formed spontaneously.
The point is:
the party cannot work in all areas
of the working class alone.
The party must work closely
with these organizations
to connect these organizations
in favor of the emancipatory struggle.
He must centralize
the tactics of these organizations.
How? Forcibly? No,
through persuasion.
Party members will join these organizations,
talk to the workers,
convince the workers,
demonstrate the need
to fight by example,
approach these organizations
and win the political support
of the masses.
The Bolshevik party did
exactly that.
not make a revolution
until it gained
a majority in the soviets.
The soviets were
the main organs of the working class;
the party worked
closely with the soviets
trying all the time to convince
the soviets of the need for a revolution,
It managed to convince the class,
won a majority in the soviets,
and then he led a revolution.
Lenin not only theorized,
but he also did!
He applied it!
Do you get how important this dude is?
So, the party has
two functions (in short, okay?)
Leading the class
into the revolution
and, after the revolution,
maintaining the revolution;
that is, it has a pre-revolution
and a post-revolution function.
Regardless of what you think
of everything I said;
“Oh Ian, I don't like it.
Not at all.
I found the party... bad.
I found it authoritative. Did not like it";
Regardless of
what you think,
Lenin's method is extremely efficient.
Ever heard of China? Cuba?
Korea? Vietnam? Albania? Burkina Faso?
Everyone, each one of them
used the Leninist method.
Regardless of
what you think,
Leninist party is an extremely
efficient method
for the seizure of power by the class.
Extremely efficient.
So, let's go.
Shall we review?
“Party." The Leninist party is:
the “organized detachment of the class”.
This detachment
must be a “vanguard”;
i.e. to be at the head of the class,
not above.
That party must be
“armed with theory”,
revolutionary theory.
This party has willing
and ironclad discipline.
That party “must mobilize
the class for the Revolution”,
and after the revolution
“it must maintain the revolution”.
That's the party.
There are many, many, other
Leninist elements about the organization
and other things.
The point is:
Lenin was a machine.
The guy wrote compulsively.
When he had a stroke,
the doctors had to ask for God's sake
for him to stop writing, for him not to die.
He was limited to writing ten minutes a day
so he wouldn't have another stroke.
Lenin is a Marxist machine.
In order to understand the organization,
you have to read Lenin.
You really have to read it.
Let's head into the end, folks!
Remember I said I was going to give you
a reading guide for you to delve into?
So, let's get into
our reading guide,
and what I'm going to
talk about is this:
I'm going to suggest an order,
which is the one
that I'm going to present here.
All the books,
except the one on the screen,
will be available for free
in the video description.
So, let's go.
If you, after watching the video,
are still feeling insecure,
read this book by Grespan,
“Marx: an introduction”.
It's a super short book
that serves to introduce everyone
to the Marxist vocabulary,
and I recommend it even
to anyone who wants to learn to teach Marxism,
because it is a very didactic book.
There, the first text
I suggest after this video
is a very short text
by Lenin
called “The Three Sources
and Three Component Parts of Marxism”.
It's a text that Lenin wrote
on the 30th anniversary of Marx's death,
and Lenin talks about the Marxist sources
that have precisely
these three elements that we talked about:
philosophy, politics, and economics.
I highly recommend reading it,
it is a very small
and very enlightening text.
Remembering that Lenin did not have access
to all of Marx's texts, which we have access today.
So, there are texts that are missing,
simply because he did not have access to them.
Next. There are two together here,
look:
“Basic Principles of Communism”
by my boy Engels,
and “Manifesto of the Communist Party”
by homies Marx and Engels.
A little story for you:
Marx and Engels, in the 1840s,
joined something called the League of the Just.
What was the League of the Just? It was
an organization of emigrants from Germany,
which was a mixture
of German idealism and utopian socialism.
Marx and Engels enter the league
under the condition that they can change
the political line of the league.
So, they: change the name of the League of the Just
to the League of Communists;
change the motto from “all men are brothers”
to “workers of all countries, unite!”;
and are in charge of writing
the League's program.
At the first meeting of the League,
Engels goes, but Marx doesn't.
And then Engels is
in charge of writing
and he writes this book,
“Basic Principles of Communism”.
But he writes in the form of a catechism,
in questions and answers.
Marx doesn't like
the catechism format
and proposed the manifesto format.
And then they together write
“The Manifesto of the Communist Party”.
The first book by Engels,
Basic Principles of Communism,
was never published.
Not in life,
it was published later.
There are topics that Engels doesn't answer,
because it was a draft.
The Communist Manifesto
is a very important book,
because it is
the most well-finished first book on Marxism
with all its core elements.
It has three important things:
a historical analysis
as a starting point;
the perspective of classes as an axis;
and to place the proletarian class
as revolutionary,
a revolutionary subject.
The Communist Party Manifesto
is the most important
political document in history.
That document
changed the world.
Well worth reading and rereading
and reading again.
Moreover: in 1877,
Engels already old,
already elderly,
writes a book called
“Anti-Dühring”,
which is a critique of the philosophy
of a guy called Eugen Dühring.
Engels makes
such a concise critique,
and expounds Marxism
so competently,
that the book is somewhat
of an unexpected success.
And then he extracts
three chapters from Anti-Dühring,
which is a big book,
and publishes it
as this book here:
“From Utopian Socialism
to Scientific Socialism”
in which he talks about
some utopian thinkers
and contrasts with the thought
of historical and dialectical materialism.
This one is very interesting,
equally short,
and well worth reading.
One more:
“Value, Price and Profit”.
Value, Price and Profit
is a lecture given by Marx
in 1865 to the International
Workers' Association.
And in that book,
Marx is just talking about
how the wage is not related
to the price of the commodity.
And here, to explain this,
he explains value and surplus value.
So, I recommend it too.
It is a short text because it is a lecture;
and I recommend it as Marx's first text
on the critique of political economy.
But if you're feeling daring;
The critique of political economy,
Marx's magnanimous
"Capital".
Capital is three books,
three huge books, like that,
which took him 16 years to write.
It's worth reading.
But if you're not feeling so daring,
I'll recommend another book:
“Handbook of Political Economy”
by the Academy of Sciences of the Soviet Union.
It's an equally gigantic book;
but it has,
due to the Soviet experience,
an excerpt that Capital does not have,
which is about the socialist mode of production.
So, if you have these doubts like:
“how is the organization of work under socialism?”
“How is surplus value in socialism?”,
“how is the factory in socialism?”,
“How is the mode of production?”, and such;
this book talks about it.
I recommend these two, okay?
But they are gigantic books,
they are not books to leave by your bedside
and read every night, they are to be consulted.
One more:
“The German Ideology”.
Lenin did not have access to this text.
This text is a text that
Marx and Engels wrote in 1846,
criticizing the Young Hegelians,
and it's the best example
we have of historical materialism.
Despite the book being gigantic,
I recommend only the first chapter,
the most important one,
which is “Feuerbach”.
That book was the one I read in college
to understand historical materialism.
It looks big, but in fact
only the first chapter is the most essential.
One more:
“Critique of the Gotha Program”.
“Oh, Ian,
I don't even know what Gotha is.
Why would I read this book
when I don't even know what Gotha is?"
The Gotha Program
was the program
for the unification of German workers' parties.
Marx, when criticizing
the unification program of these parties,
Expounded much more
about socialism.
So, he talks about:
a dictatorship of the proletariat,
the first phase of communism,
the higher stage of communism,
talks about the role of the State.
He talks about the period
of transition from socialism to communism.
This book is very important;
it's short, too. Very short.
And then, moving on
to Lenin.
People say all the time:
“read Lenin, read Lenin!”
Let's read Lenin then,
shall we?
First book:
“What is to be done?”.
What is to the done? is a book
that Lenin writes in 1902,
for the Second Congress
of the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party.
Lenin was part of a party at that time,
the Russian Social Democratic Workers' Party,
and he writes this book
to present his party ideas,
that would become the Leninist Party
in Congress.
This book is a perfect example
of how Lenin thought about
revolutionary party organization.
One more:
“The State and the Revolution”.
This book is a book that is even good
to read as Lenin's first book, too.
Why?
Here, Lenin talks about
the role of the State in a revolution
— Much like what Marx does
in the Critique of the Gotha Program —
talking about what is
the role of the State in a revolution,
how the working class
should manage the State,
what is it for;
and what is the State,
he theorizes about the State, too.
This book here,
if you're going to read it,
is Marx and Engels through and through.
Here you can see
how he mastered the subject.
And finally, a part of Leninist theory
that I haven't mentioned
but is
just as important.
Lenin identifies
that capitalism has entered a new phase:
the imperialist phase.
Capitalism expands in such a way
that it becomes monopoly capitalism,
and the countries
at the center of capitalism
begin to dispute
the division of the territory of planet Earth
for resources.
Lenin theorizing
the new phase of capitalism
is what made
the Russian Revolution possible, folks.
So, this book here [Imperialism,
the Highest Stage of Capitalism] is essential,
because imperialism
is still our greatest enemy.
Understanding the role
of imperialism in global capitalism
is fundamental to
any revolutionary perspective, anyone.
I will leave all these books
for free in the description, free of charge.
All are available on marxists.org,
in Portuguese,
except for this one.
This one, as Mr. Jorge Grespan
needs to pay his bills,
this book here
needs to be purchased.
But that's it, folks.
This was today's video,
"Basic Principles of Communism".
I hope
you've learned something.
It's a video I made
to be consulted,
and I encourage you
to ask questions.
If you want to ask me something
unclear, you can ask me.
I just don't promise to reply quickly
because I've been getting a lot of messages.
But I do my best
because as a teacher I need
to answer questions like that too.
[Subtitles by GTRR]